Guide to the Jewish Labor Committee Photographs PHOTOS 048
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jewish Labor Committee Photographs
1930s-1980s
1940-1959
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.)
PHOTOS 048
10.5 Linear Feet in 7 record cartons, 3 manuscript boxes, and 2 oversize flat boxes
The Jewish Labor Committee was founded in 1934 for the purpose of organizing opposition to fascism and providing assistance to its victims. It maintained close contact with European resistance movements, and was able to effect the rescue of several thousand labor and socialist activists, their families and other refugees. After World War II, the Committee continued its program of relief to Holocaust victims and reconstruction of Jewish culture by financing Yiddish libraries, schools, and cultural centers throughout Europe and Israel, in addition to campaigning for trade union rights and against religious discrimination. The bulk of the material relates to the years immediately following World War II through the 1950s, and includes many photographs relating to the Committee's relief programs for Holocaust victims, especially children. Of special interest are images of the children's performances: singing, dancing, theater. Also depicted are supporters, including: David Dubinsky, Leon Blum, and Jacob Pat. In addition, there are images of Committee-supported Yiddish libraries, schools, and cultural centers, as well as, several hundred portrait photographs of individual children from the Committee's Child Adoption program.
(2x2, 8x10; b&w)
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The first shipment of the Jewish Labor Committee Records arrived at the Tamiment Library in 1984. The accession numbers associated with these donations are 1984.002 and 1984.006. A number of addition donations to the collection have been made by the JLC and its individual members over the years. The accession numbers associated with the photographs donated by JLC and its members are 1984.015, 2011.091, NPA.1991.001, NPA.1991.005, NPA.1991.011, NPA.1995.024, NPA.1996.015, NPA.2003.023, NPA.2005.160 and NPA.2009.026.
Arrangement
Within each series, the progression is from the specific to the general (i.e., in SERIES I, SUBSERIES D, the arrangement moves from JLC-sponsored civil rights activities to general photographs related to the civil rights movements).
The files are grouped into 5 series:
Missing Title
Series I: General Activities, 1930s-1980s
Series II: Personalities
Series III: Aid To Children
Series IV: Photograph Albums And Oversized Photographs
Series V: Unprocessed
Historical/Biographical Note
The Jewish Labor Committee, an umbrella group of Jewish trade unions and fraternal organizations, was founded in 1934 for the purpose of organizing opposition to fascism and providing assistance to its victims. It maintained close contact with European resistance movements and was able to effect the rescue of several hundred labor and socialist activists and their families, as well as other refugees. After World War II, the Committee continued its program of relief to Holocaust victims, providing regular shipments of food, clothing, and medical supplies. It cooperated with other Jewish agencies in helping reunite families, and organized a "Child Adoption" program through which American trade unionists supported thousands of destitute children. The Committee contributed to the reconstruction of Jewish culture after 1945 by financing Yiddish libraries, schools, and cultural centers throughout Europe and Israel. In addition, the Committee has campaigned for trade union rights in the United States and abroad, and against anti-Semitism and other forms of racial and religious discrimination.
Related Archival Materials at the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.) Records, Part I (WAG 025.001)
Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.) Records, Part II (WAG 025.002)
Jewish Labor Committee Records, Part III (WAG 025.003)
Jewish Labor Committee, Boston Records (WAG 159)
Jewish Labor Committee, Chicago Records (WAG 160)
Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.) Oral History Collection (OH 027)
Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.) Photograph Collection (PHOTOS 048) Julius Bernstein Papers (WAG 116)
Edward S. Goldstein: Jewish Labor Committee Research Files (WAG 232)
Isaiah Minkoff Papers (WAG 086)
Jacob Pat Papers (WAG 127)
Baruch Charney Vladeck Papers (TAM 037)
In 1997, the Tamiment Library created a
web exhibit
that features more than 100 graphics from Tamiment's JLC collection.
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of this material is concentrated in the years immediately following World War II and in the 1950s, and includes many photographs relating to the Committee's relief programs for Holocaust victims, especially children. Most of these photographs were shot in Europe (including Austria, Belgium, England, Germany, Italy, Poland, Sweden, and Switzerland, but with the largest number shot in France) and in Israel. They are particularly strong in images of children's homes supported by the Committee--often in concert with the Workmen's Circle or United States labor unions. These include images of the exteriors of the homes themselves (several are quite impressive, resembling small chateaux), and of various activities within them: children at meals, in class, playing, getting dressed, being examined by medical personnel, etc. Of special interest are images of the children's performances: singing, dancing, theater. Also depicted are visitors/supporters of the homes, including David Dubinsky, Leon Blum, Jacob Pat, and others. In addition, there are several hundred portrait photographs of individual children supported by the Committee through its Child Adoption program. The collection also includes images of Yiddish libraries, schools, and cultural centers financed by the Committee in Europe and in Israel, photographs of performances by two Yiddish/Jewish theater groups in postwar Germany (the Baderekh Theater in Berlin and the "Mit" Theater in Munich), images of displaced persons camps, and of the activities (demonstrations, summer camps, performances) of European organizations allied with the Committee, such as the Jewish Labor Bund, Left Poalei Zion, and SKIF (the youth arm of the Bund).
The collection is arranged and subdivided as follows:
Series I-General Activities, 1930s To 1980s:
Subseries A: Establishment of JLC and Early Activities
Subseries B: Holocaust and Jewish Life in Europe Under the Nazis
Subseries C: Postwar Aid Activities
Subseries D: Anti-Discrimination and Pro-Human Rights Activities
Subseries E: Other Postwar Activities
Subseries F: JLC Staff, Branches, Chapters, Divisions, and Committees
Subseries G: Miscellaneous
Series II-Personalities:
Subseries A: JLC Leadership
Subseries B: General
Series III-Aid to Children:
Subseries A: Child Adoption Program
Subseries B: European Orphanages and Children's Homes and Other Child Aid Activities (except for France)
Subseries C: Children's Homes and Orphanages and Other Child Aid Activities in France
Series IV, Oversized Albums and Panorama Portraits
Folder labels denote series, subseries, individual folder numbers, and topic. For example, the folder entitled "Wartime food and clothing drives and other activities" is labeled as follows: I-A-3: Wartime food and clothing drives and other activities (i.e. Series I, Subseries A, Folder 3).
In addition, two appendices provide more information on the contents of the collection. They consist of a partial guide to photographs of prominent individuals represented in Series I of the collection (
see Appendix 1
Series II: Personalities also has photographs of the same and other individuals), and a list of translations of the Yiddish captions/annotations for nearly all the images that have such notations --a total of approximately 1700 photographs
(see Appendix 2)
.
Separated Materials
This collection is comprised of photographs that were separated from the Tamiment Library's Jewish Labor Committee Records, Parts I, II, and III (WAG 025.001, WAG 025.002, and WAG 025.003) as these collections were processed during the 1990s and 2000s.
Race discrimination.; Antisemitism.; Employee rights.; World War, 1939-1945 |x Civilian relief |v Pictorial works.; Children |x Institutional care |z Europe |v Pictorial works.; Photographic prints.; Jews |z Europe |v Portraits.; Demonstrations |z Europe |v Pictorial works.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Jews -- Rescue.; Jewish refugees |z Europe |v Portraits.; Theater, Yiddish |z Germany |v Pictorial works.; Children |z Europe |v Portraits.; Refugee camps |z Europe |v Pictorial works.; Jewish libraries |z Europe |v Pictorial works.; Jewish labor unions |z United States.; Anti-fascist movements |z Europe.; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Labor leaders |z United States |v Portraits.; Resistance movements, War |z Europe.; Holocaust survivors |z Europe |v Portraits.; Labor leaders |z Europe.; Socialists |z Europe.; Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring; Vladeck, B. (Baruch), 1886-1938; Gebiner, Benjamin A. -- |v Portraits; Held, Adolph, 1885-1969. -- |v Portraits; Dubinsky, David, 1892-1982. -- |v Portraits; Tabachinsky, Benjamin -- |v Portraits; Ogólny Żydowski Związek Robotniczy "Bund" w Polsce; Meiksin, Bella. -- |v Portraits; Pat, Jacob, 1890-1966 -- |v Portraits; Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.); Blum, Léon, 1872-1950 -- |v Portraits; Mehring, Bertha--Portraits.
- Series I: General JLC Activities
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains photographs related to JLC's activities from its founding until the 1980s, not including its post-World War II programs of aid to Jewish children in Europe (see Series III for child aid programs).
  - Subseries A: Establishment and Early History
    Includes photographs related to JLC's early history (1934-45), including the organization's establishment in 1934, meetings and conventions in the 1930s, the counter-Olympics it organized in August 1936, and food and clothing drives to aid victims of fascism in the 1940s. It also contains a smaller number of photographs indirectly related to JLC's WWII activities, including photographs of the International Ladies' Garment Workers Union (ILGWU)'s wartime activities, Jewish refugees from Hitler in England, the Jewish Brigade of the British Army, the liberation of the Jews of Tunisia at the hands of the British, and photographs of Jewish communal efforts on behalf of refugees from Hitler who were forced to flee into Poland in the late 1930's.
    - Establishment of JLC and early activities, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - World Labor Athletic Carnival (Counter-Olympics), Randall's Island, New York City, 1936, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Wartime food and clothing drives and other activities, United States, ca.1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - World War II photos, United States, misc., ca.1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Wartime England, ca.1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Jewish refugee aid in Poland and Romania, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Subseries B: Holocaust and Jewish Life in Europe under the Nazis
    Contains photographs related to the Holocaust. The bulk of the photographs consist of poor-quality copy prints of news service photographs of concentration camps and other Nazi atrocities. However, this subseries also contains photographs of the JLC's April 1945 Heroes and Martyrs of the Ghettos exhibition commemorating anniversary of the 1943 Warsaw Ghetto uprising. Other original photographs in the subseries include several pictures of unidentified Nazi personnel.
    - JLC Heroes and Martyrs of the Ghettos exhibition, Apr 1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - JLC Heroes and Martyrs of the Ghettos exhibition, Apr 1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Belgium, ca.1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Czechoslovakia and Romania, ca.1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - France, antisemitic exhibition, ca.1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - France, Jewish partisans and general resistance movement, ca.1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - France, German atrocities, ca.1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Germany, Liberation of concentration camps, ca.1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Netherlands, ca.1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Poland, ca.1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Unidentified Nazi personnel, ca.1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Refugees, photos produced by or for the American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee, ca.1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Subseries C: Postwar Aid Activities
    Documents the JLC's aid to Holocaust survivors and others in Europe and Israel in the first years after World War II (1945-early 1950s). It includes images depicting the JLC's food, clothing and book drives, and its "Relative Search" program. Most photographs in this subseries portray various aspects of the postwar renewal of Jewish life and culture in displaced persons camps, in European cities, and in Israel. (See also Series IV for an album of photographs of Left Poale Zion projects in Israel.)
    - Food and clothing drives, ca.1945-1950s; 1945-1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Book fund and pro-immigration activities, ca.1945-1950s; 1945-1959 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Relative search, ca.1945-1950s; 1945-1959 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Appeals for help and thank-yous from individual refugees and Holocaust survivors, with photos, ca.1945-1950s; 1945-1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Refugee visa applications with photo portraits of Holocaust survivors, ca.1945-1950s; 1945-1959 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous portraits of refugees and Holocaust survivors, location unidentified, ca.1945-1950s; 1945-1959 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Austria, Displaced persons' camps and Holocaust survivors, ca.1945-1950s; 1945-1959 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Belgium, Left Poale Zion and miscellaneous postwar Jewish activities, ca.1945-1950s; 1945-1959 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - China, Jewish refugees, ca.1945-1950s (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - France, JLC delegations, ca.1945-1950s (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - France, Hakol bekhol puppet theater, ca.1945-1950s (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - France, Miscellaneous postwar, ca.1945-1950s (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Germany, Displaced persons' camps, ca.1945-1950s (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Germany, Mit theatrical troupe, ca.1945-1950s (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Germany, Baderech theatrical troupe, ca.1945-1950s (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Germany, JLC delegations, ca.1945-1950s (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Germany, Wolpert-Goldman visit, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Germany, Miscellaneous portraits and identity documents of refugees and Holocaust survivors, ca.1945-1950s (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Germany, Miscellaneous postwar, ca.1945-1950s (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Italy, JLC delegations and aid, ca.1945-1950s (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Italy, Bundist Oyfboy Workers Collective, ca.1945-1950s (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Italy, Miscellaneous portraits of refugees and Holocaust survivors, ca.1945-1950s (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Poland, Jewish Labor Bund activities, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Poland, Left Poale Zion activities, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Poland, Jacob Pat's visits, 1946, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Poland, Miscellaneous portraits and identity documents of refugees and Holocaust survivors, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Poland, Miscellaneous postwar, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Romania, Miscellaneous portraits of refugees and Holocaust survivors, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Sweden, Jewish Labor Bund and Left Poale Zion activities, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Switzerland (Geneva), Central Jewish Library, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Palestine/Israel, JLC aid to (United States), ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Palestine/Israel, JLC delegations, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Israel, Brith Ha'avodah cooperative workshops, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Israel, Brith Ha'avodah summer camps, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Israel, Beit Lessin Cultural Center, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Israel, Kursky Library and Zygielbojm Auditorium, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Israel, Moshav Norge, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Israel, Zygielbojm children's house, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Palestine/Israel, Yiddish afternoon schools, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Israel, Workmen's Circle Neve Hadassah summer camp, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Israel, Workmen's Circle Yiddish theater groups, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Palestine/Israel, Holocaust survivors, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Palestine/Israel, Miscellaneous, ca.1945-1950s (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Subseries D: Anti-Discrimination and Human Rights Activities
    Contains images related to the JLC's postwar support of AFL and CIO (later AFL-CIO) educational efforts in the field of human rights, as well as the JLC's work of combatting antisemitism worldwide. The majority of the photographs are of labor conferences on civil rights in Chicago and other United States cities, National Trade Union Council anti-discrimination activities, and rallies in support of the rights of Soviet Jewry. Individual folders document the work of JLC local chapters for these causes. There are also several pictures of JLC protest rallies and conferences on behalf of Polish Jews.
    - JLC Fourth National Trade Union Conference on Civil Rights, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - National Trade Union Council, 1950s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - National Trade Union Council, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - National Trade Union Council, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Anti-discrimination activities/AFL-CIO meetings, California, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Anti-discrimination activities/AFL-CIO meetings, Connecticut, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Illinois (Chicago), labor conferences on civil rights, 1955-1959 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Illinois (Chicago), labor conferences on civil rights, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Illinois (Chicago), labor conferences on civil rights, 1963-1984 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Illinois (Chicago), labor conferences on civil rights- Miscellaneous, unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Anti-discrimination activities/AFL-CIO meetings, Massachusetts, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Anti-discrimination activities/AFL-CIO meetings, Michigan, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Anti-discrimination activities/AFL-CIO meetings, New Jersey, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Anti-discrimination activities/AFL-CIO meetings, New York City, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Anti-discrimination activities/AFL-CIO meetings, New York State, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Anti-discrimination activities/AFL-CIO meetings, Ohio, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Anti-discrimination activities/AFL-CIO meetings, Oregon, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Anti-discrimination activities/AFL-CIO meetings, Pennsylvania, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Anti-discrimination activities/AFL-CIO meetings, Texas, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Labor Conference on Civil Rights, Washington D.C., 1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Anti-discrimination activities/AFL-CIO meetings, Wisconsin, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Canada, AFL-CIO meetings, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Anti-discrimination activities/AFL-CIO meetings, miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Civil rights movement, miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Soviet Jewry rally, New York City, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Soviet Jewry rallies, New York City, 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Soviet Jewry rallies, New York City, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Soviet Jewry rallies, New York City, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Other Soviet Jewry activities/materials (i.e., seminars, meetings with officials, antisemitic Soviet cartoons), undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Soviet Jewry activity, United Federation of Teachers, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Soviet Jewry activity, Local JLC chapters (Illinois, Pennsylvania, Washington, DC), undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Protests against Polish antisemitism, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Labor Human Rights Award Dinner (1973): Honoring Floyd E. Smith, December 1973 (Box 10)
    - Labor Human Rights Award Dinner (1975): Honoring Albert Shanker, December 9, 1975 (Box 10)
    - Labor Human Rights Award Dinner (1977): Honoring Sol C. Chaikin, January 1977 (Box 10)
    - Labor Human Rights Award Dinner (1978): Honoring Martin J. Ward, March 29, 1978
    - Labor Human Rights Award Dinner (1979): Honoring John Lyons, September 1979 (Box 10)
    - Labor Human Rights Award Dinner (1980): Honoring Charles Pillard, December 10, 1980
    - Labor Human Rights Award Dinner (1984): Honoring Edward J. Cleary, December 1984 (Box 10)
    - Labor Human Rights Award Dinner 1985): Honoring Lynn Williams, December 10, 1985 (Box 10)
    - Labor Human Rights Award Dinner (1988): Honoring Robert Georgine, December 8, 1988 (Box 10)
    - Labor Human Rights Award Dinner (1997): Honoring Stern, Matarazzo, Hirsch, January 15, 1997 (Box 10)
    - Labor Human Rights Award Dinner (1998): Honoring Feldman, Karp, Malloy, January 27, 1998 (Box 10)
    - Labor Human Rights Memorial Tribute (1982): Jerry Wurf, January 7, 1982 (Box 10)
    - Labor Human Rights Award Dinner (1975): Honoring Murray Finley, January 1975 (Box 10)
  - Subseries E: Other Postwar Activities
    Documents the JLC's work in international labor relations, Holocaust commemoration and education, and other programs and projects. The bulk of the photographs are of JLC annual conventions and meetings. The subseries also contains pictures of JLC meetings with international labor leaders, and the organization's participation in international labor conferences, labor rallies in support of Israeli democracy and other causes. There are several images of annual Warsaw Ghetto Memorial commemorations and of courses on the Holocaust for educators run in conjunction with the United Federation of Teachers.
    - International contacts: visits of European labor and socialist leaders to U.S.; visits of U.S. leaders abroad, 1940s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - International contacts: visits of European labor and socialist leaders to U.S.; visits of U.S. leaders abroad, 1940s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Relations with Israel: Israel rallies; visits to Israel, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Holocaust commemoration and education, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Commemorations and memorials, miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Demonstrations and rallies, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - JLC exhibitions and displays, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Mensheviks, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - William Green testimonial dinner and dedication of bust, 1947, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Dedication of William Green Human Relations Library, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Atran Center for Jewish Culture, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Dedication of Philip Murray bust, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - B. Charney Vladeck memorial meeting, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - JLC conventions and meetings, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - JLC conventions and meetings, 1940s-1950s (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - JLC conventions and meetings, 1940s-1950s (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - JLC conventions and meetings, 1940s-1950s (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - JLC conventions and meetings, 1960s (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - JLC conventions and meetings, 1960s (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - JLC conventions and meetings, 1960s (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - JLC conventions and meetings, 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - JLC conventions and meetings, 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - JLC conventions and meetings, 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Triangle Fire Memorial, 2006 (Box 10)
    - JLC Conventions, 1969, 1971 (Box 10)
  - Subseries F: JLC Staff, Branches, Chapters, Divisions, Committees